Guide to the Carl E. Ladd papers,1932-1943
Ladd, Carl E. papers, 1932-1943
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Carl E. Ladd papers, 1932-1943.
21-2-87
Carl E., Ladd 1888-1943.
24 cubic ft.
Curricula, budgets, printed material, clippings, correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes curricula, budgets, printed material, clippings, and memoranda and correspondence with Cornell faculty and administrators, students, county extension agents, agricultural club leaders, farmers, publishers, state and federal agricultural agencies, credit associations, and state and national politicians. Subjects include administration of the College of Agriculture; appointments, promotions, and resignations of faculty and administrators; Farm and Home Week at Cornell; construction of the Arboretum; the Bailey Hortorium; the Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities; the Farm Credit Administration; GLF; USDA Extension Service; Dartington Hall and the South Devon cattle; the Emergency Food Commission; farm labor during World War II, wartime agricultural production, and wartime student enrollment; the "Farm Forum" broadcast on WGY; rural electrification, Dutch elm disease, and rural education. Major correspondents include Charles Poletti, Herbert H. Lehman, Eleanor Roosevelt, Howard E. Babcock, Henry A. Wallace, Flora Rose, Edward Eastman, Leonard K. Elmhirst, and the Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva, New York.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Carl Ladd received a Ph.D. from Cornell University in 1915; was Director of the New York State School at Delhi, specializing in agricultural education; Extension Professor at Cornell, 1920-24; Director of Extension, 1924-32; and was Dean of the New York State College of Agriculture, New York State College of Home Economics, and Director of Experiment Stations, 1932-43. He was a member of the New York State Planning Council; Secretary of the Governor's Agricultural Advisory Commission; and a member of the Executive Committee, Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities.
Carl Edwin Ladd was born 25 Feb. 1888 in McLean, Tompkins County, New York, at the farm of his parents, Arnold D. and Mary E. (Mineah) Ladd; he was their second son and the youngest of three children. Both parents were natives of Tompkins County; his father was descended from Daniel Ladd, who came from England to Massachusetts in 1634. Carl attended local schools and at fifteen entered the nearby Cortland (N.Y.) Normal School, from which he graduated in 1907. After a year as school principal in South Otselic, N.Y., he enrolled in the College of Agriculture at Cornell University. He received a B.S. degree in 1912 but stayed on for graduate study in the department of farm management, specializing in cost accounting under the direction of Prof. George F. Warren, whose economic ides he was to share, during the agricultural crisis of the early 1930s. He received the Ph.D. in 1915.
That year Ladd became director of the New York State School of Agriculture at Delhi, one of six regional schools recently established to provide a two year program in applied agriculture. In 1917 he assumed overall direction of the six schools as specialist in agricultural education in the State Education Department at Albany. Two years later, he became director of the State School of Agriculture at Alfred, N.Y. Ladd returned to Cornell in 1920, as extension professor of farm management. He was made director of extension work for the College of Agriculture and the College of Home Economics at Cornell in 1924.
Carl Ladd’s career was build upon identification with the interests of New York agriculture. He regarded the extension service as a vehicle for transmitting the needs of the farmer to the college and as an agency for formulating research programs to meet those needs. As director of extension he worked closely with the State Farm Bureau Federation, using its county units as local bases of operation for the College of Agriculture; through this structure extension specialists were made available to individual farmers for consultation. Under Ladd, Cornell also continued its policy of aiding farmer cooperatives such as the Dairymen's League.
In 1932 Ladd became dean of the colleges of agriculture and of home economics and director of the agricultural experiment station at Cornell. A skilled administrator and mediator, he set up meetings at the college between farmers and the businessmen who supplied their needs. Recognizing the trend toward specialization in agriculture, he altered the focus of extension work from general farming to particular commodities. He also kept Cornell in the forefront of agricultural research, concentrating on such problems as better food packaging, dehydration, and the artificial breeding of livestock. He set up a special interdepartmental research and extension projects designed to expand the market for potatoes, an important state product, and encouraged the development of the frozen food industry in New York State.
Ladd's influence in agricultural matters extended beyond the campus. He had become widely known to the farming public at large through the columns of the "American Agriculturist," edited by his close friend Edward R. Eastman. Sensitive to the techniques of public relations, he maintained contacts in Albany and Washington and with the newspaper publisher Frank Gannett. Ladd served as secretary of the State Agricultural Advisory Commission under Gov. Franklin D. Roosevelt, and later as chairman; he became chairman of the New York State Planning Council in 1936; and he was a director of the Federal Land Bank at Springfield, Mass., a major source of credit for Northeastern farmers.
Ladd's reaction to the agricultural program of the New Deal was ambivalent. He supported the Agricultural Adjustment Act as a temporary expedient and recognized the need for some government assistance, but objected to the degree of central planning envisaged by the Roosevelt administration. As new federal agencies concerned with the farmer were created, Ladd sought with considerable success to have them administered by the existing network of county agents that made up the extension service of the various land-grant colleges. The matter was formalized at a conference in 1938 between representatives of the colleges and the federal Department of Agriculture at which a compromise (the "Mount Weather Agreement") was worked out by Ladd.
While still active as dean, he died on 23 July 1943 of a coronary attack at the age of fifty five and was buried at McLean, New York.
Gould P. Colman, Dictionary of American Biography, 1973.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes curricula, budgets, printed material, clippings, and memoranda and correspondence with Cornell faculty and administrators, students, county extension agents, agricultural club leaders, farmers, publishers, state and federal agricultural agencies, credit associations, and state and national politicians. Subjects include administration of the College of Agriculture; appointments, promotions, and resignations of faculty and administrators; Farm and Home Week at Cornell; construction of the Arboretum; the Bailey Hortorium; the Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities; the Farm Credit Administration; GLF; USDA Extension Service; Dartington Hall and the South Devon cattle; the Emergency Food Commission; farm labor during World War II, wartime agricultural production, and wartime student enrollment; the "Farm Forum" broadcast on WGY; rural electrification, Dutch elm disease, and rural education. Major correspondents include Charles Poletti, Herbert H. Lehman, Eleanor Roosevelt, Howard E. Babcock, Henry A. Wallace, Flora Rose, Edward Eastman, Leonard K. Elmhirst, and the Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva, New York.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ladd, C. E. (Carl Edwin), 1888-1943.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964.; Babcock, H. E.(Howard Edward), 1889-1950.; Bailey, L.H. (Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954.; Brigham, Reuben.; Catherwood, M. P. (Martin Paul), 1904-1978.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Donlon, Mary H., 1893-1977.; Eastman, Edward.; Elmhirst, L. K. (Leonard Knight), 1893-1974.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Gannett, Frank E. (Frank Ernest), 1876-1957.; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946.; Morrison, Frank B.; Myers, William Irving, 1891-1976.; Osborn, Lithgow.; Poletti, Charles.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rose, Flora, 1874-; Simons, L. R.; Spencer, Leland, 1896-; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965.; Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities.; Cooperative Grange League Federation Exchange.; Cornell University--Buildings.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University--Students.; Emergency Food Commission.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station.; New York State College of Agriculture--Administration.; New York State College of Agriculture--Faculty.; United States. Extension Service.; United States. Farm Credit Administration.
Titles:
American agriculturist.
Subjects:
Agricultural credit.; Agricultural credit corporations.; Agricultural education.; Agriculture--Labor productivity.; Cattle--Breeding.; College students.; Dartington Hall (Totnes, England); Dutch elm disease.; Education, Rural.; Emergency food supply.; Farmers.; Rural electrification.; World War, 1939-1945--Food supply.; Agriculturists.; College administrators.
Form and Genre Terms:
Budgets.; Curricula.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
See also Carl E. Ladd Director of Extension papers, collection #21-24-97
CONTAINER LIST
- Carl E. Ladd papers
  - Unfilable Material from Dean's Desk., 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Richtmyer, Floyd K.
  - Expense Account, Carl E. Ladd., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Congratulation., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
  - Travel Slips, Dean's Funds, Work Orders., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Addresses and Articles., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities; New York State College of Agriculture; Farm and Home Week.
  - Personal., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Sigma Xi.
  - Equipment Requests., 1931-33 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Office Memoranda., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports., 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    New York State College of Agriculture.
  - Bailey Hall, Reservations., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Perkins, Frances.
  - Budget Reductions., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Budget Reductions., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Budget Items., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Budget Items., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Budget Items., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Catherwood, Martin P.
  - Budget Items., 1930-32 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Budget, Special Research Items., 1930-32 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Budget, Special Research Items., 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Abstracts., 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Agricultural Economics., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Warren, George F.; Misner, Edward G.; Kendrick, M. Slade; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agricultural Economics.
  - Warren, George F., 1931-33 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Bond, Maurice C.; Spencer, Leland; Scoville, Gad P.; Rasmussen, Marius P.; Misner, Edward G.; United States Dept. of Agriculture.
  - Warren, George F., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Misner, Edward G.; Rasmussen, Marius P.; Boyle, James E.; Varney, Harry R.; Simons, Lloyd R.; Cooperatives; Farm and Home Week.
  - Warren, George F., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Harper, Floyd A.; Kendrick, M. Slade; Scoville, Gad P.; New York State Cttee. to Investigate the Milk Industry; Milk marketing.
  - Warren, George F., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Fogg, Verne A.; Farm and Home Week.
  - Myers, William I., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Farrand, Livingston; Morgenthau, Henry Jr.; Herbert, Gaston; Federal Farm Board; Federal Land Banks; National Farmers Union; United States Dept. of Agriculture; Agricultural credit; Farm credit legislation.
  - Myers, William I., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Morgenthau, Henry Jr.; Wallace, Henry A.; Tugwell, Rexford G.; Taber, Louis J.; Roosevelt, Franklin D.; Gray, Chester H.; United States Dept. of Agriculture; National Conference of Farm Organizations; Federal Land Banks; Agricultural credit; Agricultural credit; Price controls.
  - Myers, William I., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Wallace, Henry A.; Morgenthau, Henry Jr.; Tugwell, Rexford G.; National Conference of Farm Organizations; Federal Land Banks; Agricultural credit; Farm credit legislation.
  - Bond, Maurice C., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Cunningham, Lowell C.; Harper, Floyd A.; Hill, Forrest F.; Aplin, Richard D.; Federal Land Bank of Springfield; Farm credit legislation; Agricultural marketing; Cooperative marketing.
  - Hart, Van B., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Catherwood, Martin P.; Bond, Maurice C.; United States Dept. of Agriculture, Extension Service; American Bankers Association; Farm credit legislation; Milk marketing.
  - Spencer, Leland., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Pitcher, Perley A.; Manley, Henry S.; New York State Cttee. to Investigate the Milk Industry; Milk marketing.
  - Spencer, Leland., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    International Assn. of Milk, Food and Environmental Sanitarians.
  - Pearson, Frank A., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Luce, Henry R.; Wallace, Henry A.; Holman, Charles W.; National Milk Producers Federation; Agricultural legislation.
  - Agricultural Economics, New Building., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Warren, George F.; Parker, George W.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agricultural Economics.
  - Agricultural Economics, Equipment., 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Warren, George F.; Mann, Albert R.; Betten, Cornelius; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agricultural Economics.
  - Agricultural Economics and Farm Management, Reports on Cost of Local Government., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
    Catherwood, Martin P.; Haag, Herman M.; Hart, Van B.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agricultural Economics; Rural education.
  - Agricultural Engineering., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Riley, Howard W.; Wright, Forrest B.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agricultural Engineering; American Society of Agricultural Engineers.
  - Agronomy., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Lyon, T. Lyttleton; Mordoff, Richard A.; Fisher, Joseph T.; Bizzell, James A.; Wilson, Benjamin D.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Agronomy.
  - Romell, Lars G., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Animal Husbandry., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Morrison, Frank B.; Maynard, Leonard A.; Savage, Elmer S.; Baldwin, Charles H.; Martin, Willard S.; Ewing, Perry V.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Animal Husbandry; New York State Dept. of Agriculture and Markets; New York State Assembly Cttee. on Agriculture.
  - Animal Husbandry., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Morrison, Frank B.; Maynard, Leonard A.; Van Blarcom, Conant; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Animal Husbandry; National Livestock and Meat Board; New York State Conservation Commission.
  - Attorney, University., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Botany., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Botany; Wiegand, Karl M.
  - Buildings and Grounds., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Van Blarcom, Conant; Cornell University, Dept. of Buildings and Grounds.
  - Van Blarcom, Conant., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Van Blarcom, Conant., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
  - Business Office., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Parker, George W.
  - Statement of Accounts., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 56-58)
    Cornell University, Business Office.
  - Statement of Accounts., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 59-60)
  - Publications., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Publications., 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Special Committee to Consider Publications Situations., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Publications., 1922-32 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publications., 1928-32 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publications., 1922-33 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University Committees, Faculty, University Policy., 1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Comptroller., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Saunders, C.L.; Cornell University, Office of the Comptroller; Cornell Countryman.
  - Alumni., 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Steam Reports., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Agricultural College Council., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cornell Countryman., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Home Economics., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    New York State College of Home Economics.
  - Veterinary., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    New York State College of Veterinary Medicine.
  - Dairy Industry., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Sherman, James M.; Jackson, Howard C.; Rahn, Otto; Heard, Gerald; Elmhirst, Leonard K.; Ross, Harold E.; Guthrie, Edward S.; Dartington Hall; American Dairy Science Association; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Dairy Industry; Milk Industry Foundation.
  - Engineering., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Perkins, Frances; Cornell University College of Engineering.
  - Entomology., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Hamilton, William J.; Needham, James G.; MacLeod, Guy F.; Roosevelt, Franklin D.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Entomology; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station; Sigma Xi.
  - Entomology., 1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Matheson, Robert; Griswold, Grace H.; New York State College of Agriculture, Dept. of Entomology; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station; Sex discrimination.
  - Results of Survey Records on Fifty Four Northern Illinois Dairy Farms - Thesis., 1912 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Extension., 1925-40 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Material Prepared for Governor Lehman., 1931-33 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Lehman, Herbert H.; New York State Agricultural Society.
  - Material Prepared for Governor Lehman., 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Lehman, Herbert H.; Sibley, Harper; Gannett, Frank E.; White, Charles R.; New York State Agricultural Society; New York State Planning Council; Empire State Potato Club; Farm and Home Week; Potato industry; Rural electrification.
  - Material Prepared for Governor Lehman., 1936-37 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Lehman, Herbert H.; New York State Agricultural Society; Federal Land Bank of Springfield; New York State College of Agriculture; Agricultural prices; Farm and Home Week; Dairy industry.
  - Material Prepared for Governor Lehman., 1938-42 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Lehman, Herbert H.; Poletti, Charles; New York State Dept. of Agriculture and Markets; New York State Defense Council; Empire State Potato Club; New York State Conference Board of Farm Organizations; Agricultural legislation; National defense.
  - Speeches, Index., 1924-43 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Addresses of Welcome., 1924-36 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    American Dairy Science Association; Farm and Home Week; Agricultural economics; Agricultural education.
  - Addresses of Welcome., 1937-43 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Roosevelt, Eleanor; Lehman, Herbert H.; Taber, Louis J.; Future Farmers of America; Agricultural education; Farm and Home Week.
  - Articles Prepared for Publication., 1931-43 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    White, Charles R.; New York State College of Agriculture; New York State College of Home Economics; American Farm Bureau Federation; Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station; Rural education; Land use.
  - Speeches, Business Men, Farmer Groups, Rotary, Kiwanis, etc., 1927-36 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Sibley, Harper; New York State Bankers Association; Land use; County agents; Agricultural research.
  - Speeches, Business Men, Farmer Groups, Rotary, Kiwanis, etc., 1937-42 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Moore, Frank C.; New York Farmers, Inc.; Women's City Club of New York; National Association of Manufacturers; Agricultural economics; Farm labor; National defense.
  - Commencement Address., 1929-41 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    University of Maine; SUNY Agricultural and Technical Institute at Delhi; Land grant institutions.
  - Extension Workers, Speeches., 1925-31 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    County agents; Extension education; Agricultural economics; Land use.
  - Extension Workers, Speeches., 1932-42 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Roberts, Isaac P.; New York State College of Agriculture; Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities; Economic Outlook Conference; New York Milkshed; County agents; Extension education; Dairy industry; National defense.
  - Farm Bureau, Home Bureau, Junior Extension Meetings, Speeches., 1924-26 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    New York State Farm Bureau Federation; Cooperatives; Agricultural marketing.
  - Farm Bureau, Home Bureau, Junior Extension Meetings, Speeches., 1927-29 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    New York State Farm Bureau Federation; New York State County Agricultural Agents; Tompkins County Agricultural Association.
  - Farm Bureau, Home Bureau, Junior Extension Meetings, Speeches., 1929-34 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    White, Charles R.; New York State Farm Bureau Federation; Four-H Club Federation; Farm Credit Administration; Extension work; Dairy industry.
  - Farm Bureau, Home Bureau, Junior Extension Meetings, Speeches., 1935-41 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Cornell, Ezra; White, Andrew Dickson; Smith, Frank M.; Packard, Arthur H.; American Farm Bureau Federation; New York State Conference Board of Farm Organizations; Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities; Rural electrification; Agricultural taxation; Extension work; Land grant institutions.
  - Farm Organizations, Speeches., 1926-34 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Babcock, Howard E.; Warren, George F.; Morgenthau, Henry Jr.; Van Wagenen, Jared Jr.; Thompson, Otis A.; Eastman, Edward R.; Lehman, Herbert H.; New York State Grange; Dairymen's League Cooperative Association, Inc.; New York State Agricultural Society; New York State College of Agriculture; New York State College of Home Economics; New York State Horticultural Society; Agricultural legislation; Land use; Agricultural education.
  - Farm Organizations, Speeches., 1935-40 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Witter, Dean P.; Van Wagenen, Jared Jr.; Hedrick, Ulysses P.; New York State Agricultural Society; New York State Vegetable Growers' Association; Empire State Potato Club; New York State Grange; Grange League Federation; New York Milkshed; Agricultural research; Potato industry.
  - Farm Organizations, Speeches., 1941-42 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    New York State Horticultural Society; New York State Grange; Post-war Agriculture.
  - Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities., 1928-41 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Bailey, Liberty Hyde; Roosevelt, Theodore; Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities; United States Dept. of Agriculture; Land grant institutions; Extension education; Land use; Rural sociology.
  - Land Use and Reforestation., 1925-35 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Roosevelt, Franklin D.; New York State Forest Research Council; Institute of Rural Affairs; United States Dept. of Agriculture, Bureau of Agricultural Economics; Reforestation; Land use; Lumber industry.
  - Miscellaneous., 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Federal Farm Board; County agents; Agricultural education.
  - Miscellaneous., 1932-43 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Pyrke, Berne A.; Cornell, Ezra; White, Andrew Dickson; Sisson, George W.; New York State College of Agriculture; Farm and Home Week; World's Fair, 1939; Agricultural education.
  - Radio Talks., 1927-31 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Morgenthau, Henry Jr.; Roosevelt, Franklin D.; Barrows, Storr; Four-H Clubs; Agricultural economics; Broadcasting.
  - Radio Talks., 1932-25 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Markham, G. Emerson; New York State College of Agriculture; General Electric Company; Extension work; Agricultural education.
  - Radio Talks., 1937-39 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Agricultural education.
  - Radio Talks., 1940-43 (Box 2, Folder 45)